{"tossups": [{"question": "During an engagement in this battle, a British officer said to William Birdwood, \"You're not fighting Bashi-Bazouks now\" while defending Pozi\u00e8res [[poh-ZYEHR]]. In his book <em>The World Crisis</em>, Winston Churchill described the dismissal of this battle's planners Ferdinand Foch [[FOHSH]] and Joseph Joffree. The Mark I [[ONE]] Tank was first deployed at this battle, which was launched to relieve pressure from Verdun. For ten points, name this 1916 World War One battle named for a river in Picardy, France, at which the British sustained 420,000 casualties.", "answer": "Battle of the <b><u>Somme</u></b> (accept <b><u>Somme</u></b> Offensive)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Alexander Martin composed a funerary poem for this man after he was killed at the Battle of Germantown. This man's brother, Abner, served as the second governor of North Carolina, while this man served in the North Carolina General Assembly before becoming an officer. This man, who heavily opposed the Regulator movement, is the namesake of a city that was originally a fort defending the Cumberland River valley. Leading North Carolina's soldiers in the Pennsylvania campaign, for ten points, who was this Revolutionary War general who names a large Tennessee city?", "answer": "Francis <b><u>Nash</u></b> (accept <b><u>Nash</u></b>ville)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man narrated the documentary <em>He Is Not Dimon to You</em>, which was distributed by this man's Anti-Corruption Foundation. This man called his country's largest political faction \"a party of crooks and thieves.\" After recovering from being poisoned, this man returned home from Berlin only to be imprisoned months later. For ten points, name this Russian opposition leader described by <em>The Wall Street Journal</em> as \"the man Vladimir Putin fears most.\"", "answer": "Alexei <b><u>Navalny</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One person with this title had his deceased predecessor tried in the Cadaver Synod [[SIN-ahd]] before casting him into a nearby river. That predecessor with this title, Formosus, was later reported to have performed miracles along the banks of the Tiber. A prophecy regarding people with this title dictates that the last one named Peter will oversee the destruction of the \"City of Seven Hills.\" For ten points, what title is given to the \"holder of the Keys of Heaven,\" also known as the Bishop of Rome?", "answer": "<b><u>Pope</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bishop of Rome</u></b> before mentioned; accept Supreme <b><u>Pontiff</u></b> or Roman <b><u>Pontiff</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The first scenario of this man's campaign in Age of Empires II [[TWO]] is marked by Crucible. That scenario\u2019s introduction claims that this man's group settled at the \u201chead of the Onon River.\u201d A work subtitled \u201cClan of the Grey Wolf\u201d appears in a Koei series named for this man, in which players can control a faction led by Jamukha. In one game, this man claims, \u201cIt is easy to conquer the world on horseback.\u201d For ten points, name this ruler, whose <em>Civilization 6</em> leader ability is Mongol Horde.", "answer": "<b><u>Genghis Khan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Temujin</u></b>; accept pronunciation as [[GEN-giss]] or [[CHEN-giss]])", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A visit to the White House to celebrate this period resulted in a viral dancing video featuring the 106-year old Virginia McLaurin. Maulana Karenga spoke during the first London iteration of this period. At West Virginia State University, a 2020 convocation for this annual period included a keynote given by DeRay McKesson. A predecessor of this annual period was only a week long and included the birthdays of Abraham Lincoln and Frederick Douglass. For ten points, name this celebration observed every February recognizing African-American achievements.", "answer": "<b><u>Black History Month</u></b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country contains the world\u2019s largest ship graveyard in its city of Nouadhibou [[nwah-DEE-boo]], which was previously named for the French Minister of the Colonies, Eug\u00e8ne \u00c9tienne. This country's railroad was home to the Choum [[SHOOM]] Tunnel, a \"monument to European stupidity in Africa.\" This country's Banc d\u2019Arguin [[dahr-GAHN]] is the setting of Th\u00e9odore G\u00e9ricault's [[zheh-ree-COHS]] <em>The Raft of the Medusa</em>. The White Moors, or Bidan, enslaved many of this country's Haratines, even after slavery was abolished in 1960. Nouakchott [[NWAHK-shaht]] is the capital of, for ten points, what West African nation?", "answer": "Islamic Republic of <b><u>Mauritania</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Herodotus [[heh-RAH-duh-tis]] said this man died fighting the Massageteans [[mah-sah-geh-TEE-uns]] along the Syr Darya, while another account said he was killed by Queen Tomyris. At the Battle of Thymbra, this man defeated the army of Croesus [[KREE-sus]] and conquered the Lydian kingdom. This man's capital was at Pasargadae [[pah-SAR-gah-deh]], and he established an administrative system of satraps. This ruler's namesake Cylinder tells the story of his repatriation of the Jews after the Babylonian captivity. For ten points, name this founder of the Achaemenid [[ah-KEE-muh-nid]] Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Cyrus the Great</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cyrus II</u></b> of Persia; accept <b><u>Cyrus the Elder</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man's half-brother, Edward, was killed at Corfe Castle. This man, who created juries in his Wantage [[WAHN-tidge]] law code, paid <em>gafol</em> tributes for peace on the advice of Sigeric the Serious. At Andover, this man sponsored the confirmation of Olaf Tryggvason as a Christian. Gunhilde, and possibly Pallig Tokesen, were killed in the St. Brice's Day Massacre, which this man ordered, prompting an invasion by Sweyn [[SVEN]] Forkbeard. Losing to the Vikings at Maldon, for ten points, who was this \"poorly advised\" King of England?", "answer": "<b><u>\u00c6thelred</u></b> the Unready", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This president claimed that the passage of a Civil Rights Bill would be an act \u201cagainst the white race.\u201d Landowners with property valuations exceeding $20,000 were surprisingly pardoned after being barred from giving oaths of allegiance under this man\u2019s presidency. This one-term president was a former military governor of Tennessee who many thought would engage in Radical Reconstruction. For ten points, name this 17th president who previously served as vice president under Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b><u>A</u></b>ndrew <b><u>Johnson</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1995, the Armed Islamic Group of Algeria targeted public transportation in this country. This country's most deadly terrorist attack targeted a soccer stadium and a theatre at which the Eagles of Death Metal were playing. In 2015, al-Qaeda gunmen targeted the offices of <em>Charlie Hebdo</em> in this country. For ten points, name this country whose Gendarmerie [[zhahn-dar-meh-REE]] and National Police share responsibility for counterterrorism operations.", "answer": "<b><u>France</u></b> (or <b><u>French</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Outsized credit default swaps by an employee of this bank known as the \u201cLondon Whale\u201d resulted in roughly $6 billion in losses for it. The merger of this bank with Bank One resulted in the hiring of Jamie Dimon as its CEO. For a total price of $236 million, this bank acquired the once fifth-largest investment bank, Bear Stearn. Founded by a man who bailed out the U.S. government in 1907 and bought out the Carnegie Steel Corporation, for ten points, what is this bank, partly named for an early twentieth-century financier?", "answer": "<b><u>JPMorgan Chase</u></b> & Co (prompt on \"J.P. Morgan\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Kate Blewett studied neglect under this policy in <em>The Dying Rooms</em>. This policy created the 4-2-1 problem as well as \"little emperor\" syndrome. <em>Shidu</em> bereavement is common under this policy, which created the <em>Heihaizi</em> class of people who do not have identity documents. People moved to Hong Kong to avoid this policy, which was relaxed after the Sichuan earthquake. This policy was inspired by Song Jian at the Chengdu Meeting after he read <em>The Limits to Growth</em> and <em>A Blueprint For Survival</em>. For ten points, name this Chinese population control policy.", "answer": "<b><u>One-Child</u></b> Policy", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man lined a wooden cabinet with lightbulbs and referred to it as his \u201celectric light bath.\u201d This man\u2019s brother, William, served as his bookkeeper when he was the head of an institution originally led by Ellen White. This man headed an institution that hosted three eugenics conferences for the Race Betterment Foundation. This superintendent of Battle Creek Sanitarium realized that stale wheat which was rolled created a crispier alternative to dough. For ten points, name this American inventor and creator of cornflakes.", "answer": "John Harvey <b><u>Kellogg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's wife, Sally Hayfron, was imprisoned for saying that Queen Elizabeth II, \"Can go to hell.\" This ZANLA leader compromised in a cease-fire with Christopher Soames known as the Lancaster House Agreement. Many Ndebele [[nn-deh-BEH-leh]] were killed in this man's Gukurahundi, and he led the North Korea-trained 5th Brigade. This ZANU-PF leader gave a speech at Rufaro Stadium to announce the renaming of his nation in 1980. Canaan Banana preceded, for ten points, what man who served for thirty years as president of Zimbabwe?", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Mugabe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Under this man, Mexican films and songs gained popularity as part of the Yu-Mex craze, and this man used a yacht named Peace Ship <em>Galeb</em>. This man signed the Treaty of Bled with Georgi Dimitrov and was the first head of the Non-Aligned Movement. This man sent a letter to Stalin ordering him to stop sending assassins and threatening that he would need only one killer to assassinate Stalin. Despite reforms, this man opposed the Croatian Spring. For ten points, name this Partisan leader and president of Yugoslavia.", "answer": "Marshal Josip <b><u>Broz</u></b> Tito (accept <b><u>Tito</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At this battle, Samuel Heintzelman was tasked with attacking Sudley Springs Ford. The <em>Enterprise</em> provided balloon reconnaissance at this battle which included fighting at Blackburn\u2019s Ford. Joseph Johnston\u2019s arrival contributed to Irwin McDowell\u2019s defeat at this battle, which was the subject of a telegraph sent to Lincoln declaring \u201cThe day is lost. Save Washington and the remnants of this army.\" Fought in July of 1861 in Prince William County, Virginia, for ten points, what was this battle sometimes named for nearby Manassas?", "answer": "<b><u>First</u></b> Battle of <b><u>Bull Run</u></b> (accept <b><u>First</u></b> Battle of <b><u>Manassas</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Under First Sergeant Robert John Simmons, this group stopped a Confederate</u></b> <b><u>advance at the Battle of Grimball's Landing. This group's second-in-command,</u></b> <b><u>Edward Needles Hallowell, was appointed by Governor John Albion Andrew.</u></b> <b><u>Frederick (+)</u> Douglass's sons were among the first to join this group, which trained at Camp Meigs [[MIGS]]. Augustus Saint-Gaudens [[GAW-dens]] sculpted a memorial to this group, which executed a frontal assault against Fort (*) </b>Wagner. For ten points, name this group led by Robert Gould Shaw, the first Black regiment recruited in the Northern states during the Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>54th Massachusetts</u></b> Infantry Regiment (accept the <b><u>Glory</u></b> Regiment)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2002, forgeries of this man\u2019s art peddled by con-artist Alfredo Ramos</u></b> <b><u>Mart\u00ednez led to his investigation and arrest by the FBI. This artist worked with (*)</u></b> <b>Andy Warhol on a painting called </b><em><b>Olympics</b></em><b>, with Warhol painting Olympic rings accompanied by this artist\u2019s stenciling of African mask-like heads. This artist\u2019s painting of a (*) </b>skull, <em>Untitled</em>, was sold for over $110 million, the most expensive painting by an American artist. For ten points, name this New York graffiti artist who died in 1988 from a heroin overdose.", "answer": "Jean-Michel <b><u>Basquiat</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this region, members of the Irob ruled as governors of Agame [[ah-GAH-</u><u>meh]]. This region\u2019s capital city of Mekelle [[meh-KEH-leh]] was home to the royal</u></b> <b><u>residence of Yohannes IV. The Derg faced a rebellion led by this region\u2019s namesake</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> \u201cPeople\u2019s Liberation Front,\u201d which has more recently been involved in a conflict with the government of Abiy Ahmed following a disputed 2020 election. North of the (*) </b>Amhara region and south of Eritrea is, for ten points, what region involved in an ongoing conflict with the Ethiopian government?", "answer": "<b><u>Tigray</u></b> Region (accept Region <b><u>One</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1955, Acharya Shantisagar notably performed a version of this practice</u></b> <b><u>called</u> </b><em><b><u>sallekhana</u></b></em><b><u>, which was banned by the Rajasthan High Court in 2015. In Baha'i,</u></b> <b><u>this practice begins at the end of the Intercalary Days and ends with the festival of (*)</u></b> <b>Naw-Ruz, lasting for 19 days. In Islam, this practice begins at </b><em><b>suhur</b></em><b>, and ends at </b><em><b>iftar</b></em><b>. This practice is observed during religious occasions such as (*) </b>Lent, Yom Kippur, and Ramadan. For ten points, name this religious practice in which people refrain from eating and drinking.", "answer": "<b><u>Fast</u></b>ing (accept <b><u>Sawm</u></b>; accept <b><u>Siyam</u></b>; accept equivalents such as <b><u>not eat</u></b>ing)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>Under this monarch, Alexander Bach instituted a period of neo-absolutism. A</u></b> <b><u>high collar this man was wearing likely saved him from being killed in an</u></b> <b><u>assassination attempt conducted by the nationalist J\u00e1nos [[YAH-noash]] (+)</u> Lib\u00e9nyi. The combined forces of Napoleon III and Victor Emmanuel II defeated this man's forces at Solferino. The suicide of this (*) </b>man\u2019s son, Crown Prince Rudolf, left this man's nephew as his would-be successor. Ruling for nearly 68 years, for ten points, who was this Austrian emperor?", "answer": "<b><u>Franz Joseph</u></b> I (accept <b><u>Francis Joseph</u></b> I; accept <b><u>Ferenc J\u00f3zsef</u></b>; accept <b><u>Franz</u></b> <b><u>Josef</u></b> Karl)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Mangosuthu Buthelezi left this party to found the Inkatha Freedom Party. This</u></b> <b><u>party led the Defiance Campaign against Unjust Laws after another party passed</u></b> <b><u>legislation including the Group Areas Act. This party, whose youth division operated</u></b> <b><u>the paramilitary (+)</u> \u201cSpear of the Nation,\u201d was banned by the C. R. Swart government following the (*) </b>Soweto uprising against the mandatory use of Afrikaans in schools. For ten points, name this prominent South African party of Jacob Zuma, Thabo Mbeki, and Nelson Mandela.", "answer": "<b><u>A</u></b>frican <b><u>N</u></b>ational <b><u>C</u></b>ongress (accept <b><u>ANC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The federal government forced a mandatory livestock reduction on these</u></b> <b><u>people, whom Thomas Henry Dodge represented. John MacRae Washington helped</u></b> <b><u>negotiate with this tribe, and its leader, Narbona, signed the Bear Springs Treaty. (+)</u></b> <b>Kit Carson brought these people to Bosque Redondo in the Long Walk. Led by Barboncito and Manuelito, this tribe was integrated into the (*) </b>army by Philip Johnston as code-talkers. Calling themselves the Din\u00e9, for ten points, what is this Southwest American tribe, the largest to be federally recognized?", "answer": "<b><u>Navajo</u></b> (or Naabeeh\u00f3; accept <b><u>Din\u00e9</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>As a young intelligence officer, this man was supported by explorer Fridtjof</u></b> <b><u>Nansen [[FRIT-yof NAHN-sehn]] to write a report on the League of Nations\u2019s relief in</u></b> <b><u>Kharkiv, Ukraine. Curt Brauer ordered King (+)</u> Haakon VII to appoint this man as prime minister, leading to the monarch\u2019s establishment of a government-in-exile in the U.K. The name of this leader of the Nasjonal (*) </b>Samling became synonymous with being a traitor to one\u2019s home country. For ten points, name this fascist prime minister of Norway who collaborated with the Nazi government.", "answer": "Vidkun <b><u>Quisling</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man first met his father and uncle in 1269 when they returned home</u></b> <b><u>after the Nicaean siege of Constantinople. This man sailed to Acre [[AH-kruh]] where</u></b> <b><u>he met Pope Gregory X. This man told stories to (+)</u> Rustichello da Pisa while imprisoned following the Battle of Curzola. This man\u2019s final duty to a certain empire was the delivery of Princess (*) </b>K\u00f6k\u00f6chin to her husband in Persia, after which he returned to Venice with his riches. For ten points, name this world-traveling Venetian merchant who spent time in the court of Kublai Khan.", "answer": "Marco <b><u>Polo</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Who was this Colombian leader of the Medell\u00edn [[meh-deh-YEEN]] Cartel who was killed by Colombian police at the age of 44?", "answer": "Pablo <b><u>Escobar</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}], "bonuses": []}